Register of the Ernest Batson Price Papers, 1914-1960
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest Batson Price Papers,
1914-1960
74048
Price, Ernest Batson, 1890-
13 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (5.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, diary, dispatches, writings, lecture material, photographs, and printed matter, relating to Japanese military intervention in China and Manchuria, 1931-1945; political and economic development in China, 1914-1950; and American foreign relations with China, 1914-1929.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; China.; China--Economic conditions.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--Politics and government--1912-1949.; Manchuria (China); United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; Diplomats--United States.
Biographical Note
1890, October 13 born, Henzada, Burma
1913 A.B., University of Rochester
1914-1929 U.S. Foreign Service, China
1929-1930 President, China Airways
1933 Ph.D., Johns Hopkins University
1936 Instructor, University of Chicago
1944-1945 U.S. Marine Corps Language Officer
1946-1950 associated with Standard Vacuum Oil Company. China
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1934-1959., Box 1
  Correspondence between Ernest B. Price and Japanese officials, U.S. Government officials and friends, arranged alphabetically.
- DIARY, 1947-1948., Box 1
  Personal correspondence and notes, arranged chronologically.
- HOWLAND RESEARCH PROJECT, 1932-1933., Boxes 1-2
  Charts, correspondence, maps, notes, outlines, and syllabi for a proposed book by Charles Howland, Walter Hines Page School of International Relations, John Hopkins University. This research project was not completed because of the death of Mr. Howland in 1932. Ernest Price, then assistant to Mr. Howland, undertook the project and used the collected material as a basis for his lectures at the University of Chicago.
- LECTURE AND CLASS NOTES, 1936, 1942., Boxes 2-3
  Outlines, research notes, syllabus, and class lectures that were compiled by Ernest B. Price from material used in the Howland Research Project.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1925-1960., Boxes 3-4
  Addresses, manuscripts, clippings, poems, reviews, and printed matter, arranged as listed.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1960., Boxes 4-9
  Reports, memoranda, lists, clippings, memorabilia, printed matter, and other material, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- FOREIGN SERVICE OFFICE FILES, 1914-1929., Boxes 9-11
  Correspondence, dispatches, reports, and official materials collected from assignments in China, arranged by subseries and thereunder by chronological order. The offices and positions held by E. B. Price constitute the subseries.
- CHINA AIRWAYS OFFICE FILES, 1929-1930., Box 11
  Correspondence, Contracts, proposals and office materials collected by Ernest B. Price while serving as president, China Airways, arranged as listed.
- NOTES, 1930-1942., Boxes 12-13
  Note cards, containing information on Asia, arranged as listed.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1934-1959.
  - Gubser, Charles S. (Box 1)
  - Judd, Walter
  - Kawasaki, Torao
  - Kinney, Henry W.
  - Lowndes, Arthur
  - Morse, Wayne
  - Saito, Hirosi
  - Special Senate Committee
  - miscellaneous
- DIARY, 1947-1948.
  - Personal correspondence and notes (Box 1)
- HOWLAND RESEARCH PROJECT, 1932-1933.
  - China's Interest in Manchuria. (Box 1)
  - Completed draft, first chapter, The Nature of Chinese Civilization, 1932.
  - Conflicts of Interest in Northeast Asia, Correspondence, 1932.
    - Ames, J. S.
    - Barnes, Joseph
    - Buell, Raymond L.
    - Carr-Saunders, A.
    - Carter, Edward
    - Field, Field V.
    - Hara, K.
    - Lattimore, Owen
    - MacMurray, J. V. A.
    - Merriman, R. B.
    - Myers, Denys P.
    - Root, Elihu
    - Rowell, Chester H.
    - Sokolsky, George E.
    - General correspondence, 1932
  - First tentative outline, by Ernest B. Price, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Maps, lists of maps, books and charts
  - Maps, Northeast Asia Project
  - Northeastern Asia Project, outlines
  - Notes and outlines
  - Statement of purpose, 1933
  - Tentative statement, The Northeast Asia Project, 1933
- LECTURE AND CLASS NOTES, 1936, 1942.
  - Research notes, Conflicts of Interest in Northeast Asia, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Conflicts of Interest in Northeast Asia, Course 464
    - Lecture nos I - IV
    - Lecture nos VI - XII (Box 3)
  - Political Science 261, duplicate file, Autumn, 1936.
  - Materials and outlines for lectures and seminars.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1925-1960.
  - An Aeroplane View of Northern Manchokuo. (Box 3)
  - All In A Day's Work.
  - American Policy In China Since V-J Day.
  - American Policy Towards China, 1958.
  - As Others See Us.
  - Beyond Human Understanding.
  - China In A Divided World.
  - China: The Summing-Up, 1944.
  - China's New Constitution And Its Protection.
  - The Chinese Communists.
  - The Chinese Concept Of Law.
  - The Chinese In Manchuria.
  - Chinese Symbolism.
  - A Close-Up Of Our Foreign Aid Program.
  - The Crisis of Democracy.
  - Extraterritoriality In China.
  - The Force Of Chinese Civilization.
  - The Future Of China.
  - International Law And Organization.
  - Leaves From A Consul's Notebook.
  - The Manchurians And Their New Deal. (Box 4)
  - My Friends The Chinese.
  - The Nature of Chinese Civilization.
  - A Question Of Color.
  - The Return Of Chang Kuo-Hua.
  - Secrets Of The Foochow Lacquer Shop.
  - Some Do's And Don'ts About China.
  - The Tiger Of Fragrant Mountain.
  - Toward Better World Patterns.
  - The Way Of Peace In Manchouko.
  - What About Formosa?
  - What Happaned In Panama?
  - What Is Manchouko?
  - What Makes Irving Fight?
  - What To Do About China?
  - Why The Chinese Nationalists Fell.
  - The World Is My Community.
  - Poems.
  - Miscellany.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1960.
  - American interests, opium suppression, 1933. (Box 4)
  - American Japanese relations, conflict of policies in China and Manchuria.
  - America's Aloofness New York Times editorial, November 30, 1937.
  - Biographical file, entry into the Foreign Service.
  - China
    - American policy towards China.
    - China and Korea.
    - China, 1945.
    - Constitution, Suggested draft of the constitution of China, circa 1914. (Box 5)
    - Cultural and social personalities.
    - Economic tariff.
    - Economy.
    - Economy, foreign trade.
    - Foreign relations, treaties.
    - Foreign relations, treaties, extraterritoriality.
    - Foreign relations, Washington conference.
    - Foreign relations with Great Britain.
    - Foreign relations with Japan.
    - Foreign relations with U.S.A., 1861-1880.
    - Foreign relations with U.S.A., 1933.
    - History, bibliographies.
    - History, pre-Manchu period.
    - History, 1912-1916.
    - Hong Kong notes, clippings and copies, 1950.
    - Kuomintang.
    - Language (Box 6)
    - Law for the emergency punishment of offenses, December 22, 1947.
    - Law of Hong Kong.
    - Nation making in China, January 1927.
    - Physical.
    - Political, Army and Navy.
    - Political, communism in China, 1927.
    - The Political Doctrines of Sun Yat-Sen, P.M.A. Linebarger.
    - Political, Functioning of government, protection of life and property.
    - Political, Government under the Tang Dynasty.
    - Political, Nationalist Government.
    - Political, Nationalist, 1930-1931.
    - Political status in Manchuria, 1932.
    - Press clippings, domestic conditions.
    - Sino-Japanese Conflict, M. Hsitien Lin, 1937.
    - Taxation.
    - Tsinan Incident, April 25, 1928-December 1, 1928.
  - Dutch East Indies, administration of the Dutch East Indies.
  - Exams, Ph.D. examinations, Johns Hopkins University, 1933.
  - Foreign aid program.
  - Foreign policy outline, Japan, China, and Russia in in Manchoukuo and Northeastern Asia, 1932.
  - Foreign policy, world politics program.
  - India, classroom notes, Stanford University, 1930. (Box 7)
  - Japan
    - Allied intervention in Siberia, 1918-1922.
    - Conflicting interests in the Far East.
    - Cultural and historical background.
    - Diplomatic Commentaries, by V. K. Ishii, 1931.
    - Emigration to Manchuria.
    - History.
    - Interest and attitudes.
    - Japan and Manchoukuo.
    - Negotiations with Japan, 1903-1904.
    - Newspaper comments.
    - Policies in Manchuria.
    - Repatriation, Japanese civilians.
    - Right to exist doctrine.
  - Johns Hopkins University, Page School appointment as research assistant, candidacy for Ph.D. degree, research project.
  - Latin American contributions to the peaceful settlement of international disputes.
  - Manchuria (Box 8)
    - Agricultural resources, 1933.
    - Communications.
    - Economics.
    - Extraterritoriality.
    - Foreign interests.
    - History.
    - Japan's domination of Manchouko.
    - Japanese interests, fisheries, oil, 1934.
    - Japanese occupation.
    - Maintenance of Manchoukuo.
    - Mineral resources, 1933.
    - Miscellaneous material.
    - Mongols.
    - Progress of Manchoukuo, 1934.
    - Railways.
    - South Manchuria Railway Company, 1937.
    - Newspaper clippings.
    - Northeastern Asia study.
    - Personal reference material.
  - Russia
    - Eastward migrations
    - General
    - Interest in Northeastern Asia, historical document.
    - Russia - Japan relations.
    - Russia - Japan, 1905 war.
    - Negotiations with Japan, 1903-1904.
    - Russians on the Amur Territory in the 17th Century.
    - Siberian Intervention of 1918-1922.
    - Soviet-German Non Aggression Pact, August 13, 1939. (Box 9)
    - Soviet Interests in Manchuria, 1924.
    - Study of regional areas in federal administration.
    - Treaties, Far Eaet.
    - Treaties, Russo-Japanese treaties of 1906-1907, concerning Manchuria and Mongolia.
    - Treaties, Russo-Japanese treaties, reviews.
    - United States Foreign Policy - China, San Francisco Chronicle Poll, 1958.
    - Vietnam.
- FOREIGN SERVICE OFFICE FILES, 1914-1929.
  - Tientsin, China, Interpreter, 1916-1919. (Box 9)
  - Canton, China, Vice Consul, 1920-1921.
  - Foochow, China, Vice Consul, 1921-1925. (Box 10)
  - Tsinan, China, Vice Consul, 1928.
  - Nanking, China, Vice Consul, 1928-1929. (Box 11)
  - Miscellany.
- CHINA AIRWAYS OFFICE FILES, 1929-1930.
  - Articles of incorporation. (Box 11)
  - Contracts.
  - Correspondence, 1929.
  - Proposals.
  - Memorandums.
  - Cables.
  - Miscellaneous data.
- NOTES, 1930-1942.
  - Note cards, Conflicts of Interest in Northeast Asia, 1942. (Box 12)
  - Note card collection, Asia, 1930's. (Box 13)